<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE part PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.1.2//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.1.2/docbookx.dtd" [
]>
<part id="ref-overview">
  <title>ModemManager Overview</title>

  <chapter id="ref-overview-introduction">
    <title>Introduction</title>
    <para>
      ModemManager provides a unified high level API for communicating with
      (mobile broadband) modems. While the basic commands are standardized,
      the more advanced operations (like signal quality monitoring while
      connected) varies a lot.
    </para>
    <formalpara>
      <title>Using</title>
      <para>
        ModemManager is a system daemon and is not meant to be used directly from
        the command line. However, a command line client (mmcli) is provided, which
        may be used to test the different functionality provided during plugin
        development.
      </para>
    </formalpara>
    <formalpara>
      <title>Implementation</title>
      <para>
        ModemManager is a DBus system bus activated service (meaning it's started
        automatically when a request arrives). It is written in C. The devices are
        queried from udev and automatically updated based on hardware events. There are
        DBus-interface specific GInterfaces, which should be implemented by any device
        specific implementation. There is a generic MMBroadbandModem implementation that
        provides a generic implementation of the most common operations in both GSM and
        CDMA modems.
      </para>
    </formalpara>
    <formalpara>
      <title>Plugins</title>
      <para>
        Plugins are loaded on startup, and must implement the MMPlugin interface. It
        consists of a couple of methods which tell the daemon whether the plugin
        supports a port and to create custom modem implementations. It most likely
        makes sense to derive custom modem implementations from one of the generic
        classes and just add (or override) operations which are not standard. Writing
        new plugins is highly encouraged!
      </para>
    </formalpara>
  </chapter>

  <chapter id="ref-overview-states">
    <title>State machine</title>
    <para>
      ModemManager implements support for each Modem by controlling their
      behaviour following the steps given in the following state machine.
    </para>
    <figure id="mm-modemmanager-states">
      <title>ModemManager states</title>
      <graphic fileref="ModemManager-states.png" format="PNG"></graphic>
    </figure>
    <para>
      The state machine of a modem can be summarized in 5 main sequences:
      initialization, enabling, connection, disconnection and disabling.
    </para>
    <section>
      <title>Initialization</title>
      <para>
        <!-- TODO -->
      </para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Enabling</title>
      <para>
        <!-- TODO -->
      </para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Connection</title>
      <para>
        <!-- TODO -->
      </para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Disconnection</title>
      <para>
        <!-- TODO -->
      </para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Disabling</title>
      <para>
        <!-- TODO -->
      </para>
    </section>
  </chapter>
</part>
